Finding Aid for Preston Family Papers, 1819-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Preston Family Papers 1819-1984, 1850-1870
Preston family.
0.5 linear feet
85448 Aa 2
St. Joseph, Berrien County, Michigan family. Papers of family members, primarily correspondence of Ann G. Loomis Preston with her father, Jonathan Loomis, and with her sons Wallace and Fowler, sailors in the Union navy during the Civil War; typescript of excerpt of Civil War diary of Wallace Preston; paper, 1978, of Harriet N. Preston based upon family Civil War experiences; photographs, clippings and miscellanea concerning family and St. Joseph, Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated to the library by members of the Preston family in 1978 and 1990 (Donor No. 6158 ).
The collection is open to research.
The Preston family included some of the first settlers to southwest Michigan (Berrien County). Sons of those early pioneers went on to become sailors on the Great Lakes and Union Navy veterans of the Civil War. After the war, the Prestons became one of the more prominent families in St. Joseph, Michigan as a result of successful business and political endeavors.
Fowler Preston was the first member of the family to travel west to Michigan. He arrived by way of the Erie Canal in 1829. Born in Massachusetts in 1800, he died at St. Joseph in November, 1843. In 1831, he was appointed captain in the militia of the Michigan Territory and later served as sheriff of Berrien County and Marshall of the village of St. Joseph. In 1836, he married Ann Jenette Loomis (1812-1891). She was also, originally, from Massachusetts.
The Prestons had three boys: Norris (1837-1856); Wallace (1842-1924); and Fowler, Jr. (1844-1896). Fowler, senior, died in 1843, a few months before the birth of his youngest son. Despite this loss, the family was able to maintain a modest living after the father's death based upon income from property acquired during the marriage and Ann Jenette Preston's own ingenuity.
The three sons all began careers as sailors on the Great Lakes. Norris, a steward on the Toledo, died in a shipwreck off the Wisconsin coast in 1856. Fowler Jr. began sailing as a cabin boy at the age of 13 and a few years later captained his own ship. With the coming of the Civil War, Fowler enlisted in the Navy in 1861. During 1861-1862, he served on several ships which were maintaining the blockade of confederate ports off the North Carolina coast. He also visited Havana, Cuba (a neutral port) while in the Union Navy. With his one-year enlistment completed, Fowler returned to Michigan.
Wallace Preston spent the early part of the Civil War shipping on the Great Lakes but, in 1863, he also enlisted in the Navy. Wallace was assigned to the U.S. Steamer Proteus which was based in Florida. The Proteus was engaged in enforcing the blockade off of Key West and Galveston. Like his brother, Wallace also returned to Michigan after military service.
Following the war, the two brothers took different paths. Fowler turned again to the Great Lakes. For the rest of his career, he owned or captained a succession of vessels which hauled lumber and other goods along the Lake Michigan coast. He died in Chicago in 1896. Wallace returned to St. Joseph where he established a successful lumber business (Champion Planing Mill). He later served in a number of political offices before becoming mayor of St. Joseph (1893-1894) on the Republican ticket. He died in St. Joseph in 1924.
In 1972, a bundle of over forty Preston family letters, dating mainly from 1850 to 1870, were discovered in the attic of the family home in St. Joseph. Over the next few years, Harriet N. Preston, wife of Arthur G. Preston, Jr. (grandson of Wallace Preston), took an interest in these letters and the Preston family history. Mrs. Preston arranged the letters, compiled typed transcripts, and authored several papers based on the letters.
The Preston family papers document Great Lakes shipping in the nineteenth century, the Union Navy during the Civil War, and daily life in St. Joseph, Michigan during the latter half of the nineteenth century. The collection has been divided into five series: Correspondence; Legal Documents; Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook and Miscellaneous Materials; Family Histories; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Berrien County (Mich.); Great Lakes.; Loomis, Jonathan.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Preston, Ann J. Loomis, 1812-1892.; Preston, Fowler S., 1844-1896.; Preston, Harriet N.; Preston, Wallace A., 1842-1924.; Preston family.; Saint Joseph (Mich.); Shipping.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Women--Michigan--Berrien County.; Women--Michigan--Saint Joseph.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Business enterprises--Michigan--Saint Joseph.; Passengers.; Saint Joseph (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Ships--Great Lakes.; Whalebacks.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence 1819-1907
  The Correspondence (1819-1907) is chronologically arranged and has been divided into originals, typed transcripts and photocopies of originals. For the most part, the photocopies are those of originals still held by the family. The majority of the correspondence is to or from Ann Jenette Preston and most of the letters date from 1850 to 1870. Correspondents include Mrs. Preston's sons as well as her parents in western Massachusetts. A two page typescript of excerpts from Wallace Preston's diary (1861) may also be found in the typed transcripts. Subjects documented in the correspondence include: a widow's life on the frontier; Great Lakes shipping especially in the 1850s; life aboard Union naval vessels during the Civil War; and daily life in St. Joseph, Michigan and western Massachusetts just before, during, and immediately after the Civil War.
  - Originals 1819-1907, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Transcripts 1819-1879, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of originals 1841-1874 (Box 1)
- Legal Documents 1828-1888
  The Legal Documents series (1828-1888) includes deeds and mortgages of the Preston family as well as other miscellaneous official papers. These documents are chronologically arranged and have been divided into originals and photocopies. Generally, the photocopies supplement rather than duplicate the originals since Preston family members currently hold some of the originals.
  - Originals 1828-1852 (Box 1)
  - Photocopies 1828-1888 (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook, and Miscellaneous Material 1866-1976
  The Newspaper Clippings, Scrapbook, and Miscellaneous Material (1866-1976) includes one folder of clippings, a scrapbook, and one folder of flyers and public announcements. Generally, these clippings and flyers document special events in St. Joseph during the 1880s and 1890s as well as Preston family commercial and political endeavors.
  - Newspaper clippings 1866-1976 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 1868-1897 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous material 1836-1930 (Box 1)
- Family Histories
  The Family Histories series includes two historical articles written by Harriet N. Preston based upon the Preston family correspondence. "Letters of Norris Charles Preston" focuses upon the correspondence between Norris and his mother and describes the daily routines of a sailor on the Great Lakes in the 1850s. The second paper, "Ann Jenette", is based on the correspondence of Ann Jenette Preston with her sons who were in the Union Navy and with her family in Massachusetts during the Civil War. Besides discussion of the sons' military experience, the paper also recounts the hardships on the home front. In addition to these histories, this folder also includes some additional research material gathered by Harriet N. Preston including a family genealogy and brief biographical sketches of family members.
  - Historical articles written by Harriet N. Preston based upon the Preston family correspondence and related materials (Box 1)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series includes six prints of family members, one of downtown St. Joseph, and one of the steamship "Whaleback" unloading at St. Joseph. All of the photographs appear to date from the turn of the century.
  - Photographs of family members and of St. Joseph, Michigan (Box 1)